<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="//purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="//purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="//search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Inside - Chris Arderne]]></title><description><![CDATA[Outside & Inside]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/</link><image><url>//rdrn.me/favicon.png</url><title>Inside - Chris Arderne</title><link>//rdrn.me/</link></image><generator>Ghost 2.2</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 14:54:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//rdrn.me/tag/inside/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[A hackathon with iRise in Mogadishu]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Together with a colleague at the World Bank, I ran a small project aimed at supporting the Mogadishu tech community. We proposed this project to the Youth Innovation Fund and were supported with a small grant to carry out the project. We worked with Awil Osman at <a href="//irisehub.so/">iRise Hub</a> to</p>]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/hackathon-irise-mogadishu/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5bbde820ec5d5922fde79bf1</guid><category><![CDATA[Inside]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Arderne]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 08:54:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Together with a colleague at the World Bank, I ran a small project aimed at supporting the Mogadishu tech community. We proposed this project to the Youth Innovation Fund and were supported with a small grant to carry out the project. We worked with Awil Osman at <a href="//irisehub.so/">iRise Hub</a> to put together <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MogadishuWatt">#MogadishuWatt</a>, focused on using technology to solve energy issues in Somalia.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">.<a href="https://twitter.com/iRiseHub?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@iRiseHub</a> just concluded Day 1 of the Bootcamp for the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MogadishuWatt?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MogadishuWatt</a> open innovation challenge, supported by <a href="https://twitter.com/WorldBank?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@WorldBank</a>. Young Somalis are innovating to <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EndEnergyPoverty?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#EndEnergyPoverty</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SDG7?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#SDG7</a> ☀️🌪🔭👩🏾‍🔧👨🏾‍🔬<br><br>More 👉🏿 <a href="https://t.co/F9IfudndLA">https://t.co/F9IfudndLA</a> <a href="https://t.co/ci7qitOhVE">pic.twitter.com/ci7qitOhVE</a></p>&mdash; Multi Partner Fund (@mpfsomalia) <a href="https://twitter.com/mpfsomalia/status/1009440875951394821?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">June 20, 2018</a></blockquote>
<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</figure><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The winner of the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MogadishuWatt?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MogadishuWatt</a> open innovation challenge is BulshoBille, a startup that provides access to solar equipment to IDPs &amp; poor families. The pay-as-you-go model provides a better &amp; affordable approach. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SDG7?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#SDG7</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EndEnergyPoverty?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#EndEnergyPoverty</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SomaliaRising?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#SomaliaRising</a> <a href="https://t.co/5eiecXncfr">pic.twitter.com/5eiecXncfr</a></p>&mdash; iRise Hub (@iRiseHub) <a href="https://twitter.com/iRiseHub/status/1012368927542927361?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">June 28, 2018</a></blockquote>
<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</figure><p>We wrote another blog post with information on some of the interesting tech projects happening in Mogadishu: <a href="//blogs.worldbank.org/ic4d/node/762">blogs.worldbank.org/ic4d/node/762</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA['Lighting the World' - A paper I worked on]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I did my Master's thesis at KTH University of Technology on <a href="//urn.kb.se/resolve?urn=urn%3Anbn%3Ase%3Akth%3Adiva-189473"><em>A climate, land-use, energy and water nexus assessment of Bolivia</em></a><em>. </em>That is, I used various models and approaches to attempt to look holistically at Bolivia's land, energy and water use, taking into account the expected impacts of climate change.</p>]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/lighting-the-world/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5bbc652a7cc70a140e7fd11e</guid><category><![CDATA[Inside]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Arderne]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 08:35:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I did my Master's thesis at KTH University of Technology on <a href="//urn.kb.se/resolve?urn=urn%3Anbn%3Ase%3Akth%3Adiva-189473"><em>A climate, land-use, energy and water nexus assessment of Bolivia</em></a><em>. </em>That is, I used various models and approaches to attempt to look holistically at Bolivia's land, energy and water use, taking into account the expected impacts of climate change. One of the models I used is called <a href="//www.onsset.org/">OnSSET</a> (EU-funding requires silly acronyms, apparently). This model is used to determine the best way to achieve universal electrification, by suggesting for each location in a country whether to extend the electrical grid, use a mini-grid system, or rather to rely on stand-alone household solar PV systems.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/b.png" class="kg-image"><figcaption>Example OnSSET results from my thesis</figcaption></figure><p>Essentially the model takes in a variety of data on population distribution, energy infrastructure, solar intensity, night-time satellite imagery, as well as social and techno-economic factors. As a starting point, it uses this to estimate where the settlements are that already have electricity access. From there, the model spreads outwards from electrified locations, and for each new location, comparing the cost of connecting by the three different options. An exhaustive (-ing?) process.</p><p>I started overhauling this model while using it for my thesis, and as a result was talked into staying at the division as a Research Engineer. In essence, the model I inherited was a complicated mix of Excel macros, copy-pasting and difficult GIS instructions. During the course of my thesis I picked up Python (a lovely task, already knowing Java) and set to work replacing the model with a coherent Python library: <a href="https://github.com/carderne/PyOnSSET">PyOnSSET</a></p><p>This made modelling a country a few orders of magnitude faster, and much easier to batch process huge jobs. So we immediately put it to work modelling the whole of Sub-Saharan Africa! The modelling unit is 1 km<sup>2</sup> (more on that later) so this involved modelling more than 20 million individual units (iteratively!). We published this in Environmental Research Letters: <em><a href="//iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/aa7b29/meta">Lighting the World: the first application of an open source, spatial electrification tool (OnSSET) on Sub-Saharan Africa</a></em></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/4.png" class="kg-image"></figure><p>The model was also used in the International Energy Agency's <em><a href="https://webstore.iea.org/weo-2017-special-report-energy-access-outlook">Special Report: Energy Access Outlook</a> </em>to show what is need to provide electricity to the millions in Africa currently without access (see the figure above, taken from the report.</p><p>Unfortunately, I left KTH and the Division for Energy Systems Analysis before getting the time to fix two of the model's biggest shortcomings:</p><ol><li>Modelling 1 km<sup>2</sup> grid cells, instead of representations of actual towns and villages. This means that a barren patch of land will get a solution, even if it's never inhabited. This is not only inefficient, computationally, but logically unsound. In the same way, larger towns and cities (anything more than 1 km<sup>2</sup>) can get split up into multiple modelling units, which doesn't make a lot of sense.</li><li>It handles time in a very simplistic way, modelling only <em>today</em> and <em>2030 </em>(or another far-off year). This doesn't exactly give policy-makers and private sector developers a good vision of where they should be going <em>tomorrow.</em></li></ol>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fun with population dynamics]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Some time, several years ago when I still very excited about Java, and read a lot of books on evolution, I had the fun idea to combine the two. I created a simple Java program (<a href="https://github.com/carderne/Altruism">here on GitHub</a>) to model one of the more interesting examples of game theory used</p>]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/population-dynamics/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5bc07fe4f6b2f324744f5439</guid><category><![CDATA[Inside]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Arderne]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 11:41:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some time, several years ago when I still very excited about Java, and read a lot of books on evolution, I had the fun idea to combine the two. I created a simple Java program (<a href="https://github.com/carderne/Altruism">here on GitHub</a>) to model one of the more interesting examples of game theory used to explain the origins of altruism (and its evolutionary benefits): <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultimatum_game">The Ultimatum Game</a>.</p><p>I'll let Wikipedia explain:</p><blockquote>One player, the proposer, is endowed with a sum of money. They are  tasked with splitting it with another player, the responder. Once the  proposer communicates their decision, the responder may accept it or  reject it. If the responder accepts, the money is split per the  proposal; if the responder rejects, both players receive nothing.</blockquote><p> So I created a simple algorithm, and since I was neck-deep in the Object-Oriented Programming way of thinking, the players in the game were naturally represented with Classes and Objects! I set up the model to accept an arbitrary number of players (in the obnoxious GIF below it was 4000) and assign each player with a 'strategy': what kind of offers they make and what kind they accept. These are represented by numbers in the model:</p><ol><li>Very generous: offers large amounts, but accepts any amount offered</li><li>...</li><li>...</li><li>...</li><li>The middling player: offers half, but only accepts if half or more is offered</li><li>...</li><li>...</li><li>...</li><li>Stingy: offers small amounts, and only accepts large offers</li></ol><p>The players then randomly play against each other, and keep track of how much they've won or not. After each round, the player with least in their coffers is... killed. Then they play again and again until there are only a few players left.</p><p>As you can see in the video below, the 5's last the longest, with there in-between strategy! Note that I didn't allow players to combine strategies, as this would have complicated it a bit, and (if I remember) there is a suggestion that the <em>offer </em>and <em>accept </em>parameters are somehow linked evolutionarily.</p><div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:84%;position:relative;"><iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/2kP4b6pXhCKLiNaYe0" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p><a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/2kP4b6pXhCKLiNaYe0">via GIPHY</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>