<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="//purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="//purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="//search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Mountains - Chris Arderne]]></title><description><![CDATA[Outside & Inside]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/</link><image><url>//rdrn.me/favicon.png</url><title>Mountains - Chris Arderne</title><link>//rdrn.me/</link></image><generator>Ghost 2.2</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 14:54:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//rdrn.me/tag/mountains/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Primero, somos tontos]]></title><description><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec25---01-after-deciding-we-needed-more-time-for-the-summit--small-hike-to-a-mini-peak.JPG" class="kg-image"><figcaption>Chris Arderne, Michael Kloos, Rick Kotze</figcaption></figure><p>We knew this already, but our three weeks in Mexico drove the message home on an almost daily basis. This is the story of three South African amigos fumbling their way up a few volcanoes and some jagged rock faces in the land of</p>]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/primero-somos-tontos/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5bbc64227cc70a140e7fd10e</guid><category><![CDATA[Outside]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mountains]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Arderne]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 08:17:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec25---01-after-deciding-we-needed-more-time-for-the-summit--small-hike-to-a-mini-peak.JPG" class="kg-image"><figcaption>Chris Arderne, Michael Kloos, Rick Kotze</figcaption></figure><p>We knew this already, but our three weeks in Mexico drove the message home on an almost daily basis. This is the story of three South African amigos fumbling their way up a few volcanoes and some jagged rock faces in the land of chillies, tortillas, piñatas and moustaches.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec31---04-looks-like-I-have-a-huge-handlebar-moustache.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><p>The plan was simple enough: keep the plan modest, and figure the details out when we get there... How difficult could two volcanoes and some rocks be? Three objectives, and three weeks to accomplish them. The plan (if it could be called that) was for Rick and Michael to head straight to the primary objective and highest peak in Mexico, Pico de Orizaba. They would start figuring things out while waiting to hear whether Chris (whose passport was precariously full) would be able to enter Mexico at all.</p><p>Looking back on it, it’s classic hubris. With Andean experience above 6 000 m, Chris felt confident the altitude would be no obstacle. Having been in the high 5 000s in the Cordillera Blanca, Michael thought he knew what he was in for. Only Rick, having suffered up Elbrus, was properly prepared to suffer again. We semi-confidently set Christmas day for our summit attempt, just four days from sea level.</p><p>And one by one we succumbed. A strenuous hike at 3 000 m laid Rick low. Our first acclimatisation hike to 4 800 m got Chris. And the next day Michael was brought down at the same height. It was a sobering blow for the Supertramps. Other people were passing through base camp and reaching the summit - most of them looking haggard and miserable on the way down. We decided that wasn’t the summit story we wanted. We wanted to get to the summit on our terms: quickly, confidently, and with the energy to enjoy it and be safe.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec28---11-back-at-camp-with-boots-around-my-neck.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/IMG_0993.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><p>So, on Christmas day, we made a tough decision: we bailed. After a rest back in town, we ate some beans and said hasta luego to Orizaba, and took the first of the buses that would bring us to Iztaccíhuatl, Mexico’s third highest peak. (Popocatépetl, the second, is currently unclimbable due to volcanic activity.) We’d been told Izta was more or less a walk up, so we stashed our technical gear in the small town of Santiago and caught a minibus taxi to the dusty base camp. In between mouthfuls of the trip’s worst tacos, we saw hikers trudging off the mountain - fully geared up with crampons and helmets...</p><p>There we were, getting ready for a short sleep and an early start up an easy mountain. And once again our over-confidence and poor planning stymied us. Morale hit an all-time low, and we regrouped in the dust-covered tent to gather our thoughts. The prospect of no Mexican summits seemed all too possible, and all too much to handle. Eventually we were able to dry our eyes and make a plan. Michael would hitchhike to Amecameca to rent some crampons, Chris would hitch to Santiago to fetch the other gear, and Rick would look after the dusty-getting-dustier tent. Finally, we could have our pre-summit dinner and go to bed.</p><p>We got up a few hours before sunrise, ready to hike the 1 300 vertical metres and seven horizontal km to the summit. And immediately got lost in the dark. Our delicate morales could hardly bear it, but after stumbling around precarious cliffs for two hours, we retraced our steps and found the very well-trodden path in the first rays of dawn. Two hours behind schedule, the day was a race against the bad afternoon weather. And to climb Iztaccíhuatl (“the white woman” in Nahuatl), you have to climb her feet and knees, cross her thighs and stomach and finally finish on one of her two... summits.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec28---02-popocatepetl-entertaining-us-in-the-early-morning-hours.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/IMG_1027.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><p>Each time we summited something, we saw how far there still was to go, and we debated whether we still had the time to make it safely there and back. Rick did his best to keep spirits high, and after about eight hours we made it to the very easy glacier crossing before the final summit scramble. Elation! We had managed to summit something! After being sure we wouldn’t make it, the relief at not having to wake up the next morning to try again was palpable. We’d spent a good few hours above 5 000 metres and it was time to scramble back to camp quickly.</p><p>The Supertramp morale was revolutionised! We felt that we could return to Orizaba and give it our best shot, safe in the knowledge that we had at least one summit shot with the MCSA Supertramp banner, should we not make it up. After a rest day eating fruit salad and unwittingly exploring the world’s largest pyramid (The Pyramid of Cholula), we returned to the base camp at Pico de Orizaba, ready for a New Year’s Eve summit the next day. Base camp was cold, windy and foggy, and chances of an easy climb seemed low, but as we turned in for our 7 pm bedtime, the skies cleared and the summit glacier beckoned promisingly to us. Suddenly we knew we would do it.</p><p>An early morning, a quick breakfast of our secret oatmeal concoction and we were on the trail by 1:30 am. We set a brisk pace and took turns telling each other to slow down. But we felt good and our legs were enthusiastic to go. We passed a few other groups, and passed our previous high point quickly. We entered the so-called ‘labyrinth’ of ice and rock before the glacier proper, but the well-worn snowpack was easy to follow in the dark. We had a quick break to drink and get out our axes, and then started the long crunch up the endless slope to the summit. The snow was perfect and firm: Chris set a good pace in front (breathing and wiggling his toes fiercely to keep them from frosting over) and the angle was just shallow enough to make the going bearable.</p><p>After an indeterminable time on the featureless slope, we zagged past a rocky outcrop, which we knew meant the summit was approaching. Feeling strong from our acclimatisation, we kicked into high gear and marched upwards. The slope steepened, then slackened, and we were there! We hit the snow-free crater-ridge (and what a crater!) just in time to welcome the first rays of daylight (and most welcome they were for our freezing toes). At 5 636 metres above sea level, the third highest point in North America, and the biggest volcano any of us had been on. After photos and a celebratory naartjie, we started loping back down the slope. Rick and Chris enjoyed sliding down the slowly softening snow, even practising some self-arrest, but the altitude had finally started to catch up with Michael.</p><p>In no time, we were off the glacier, through the labyrinth, and walking barefoot back into base camp. Feeling strong, we were very pleased with our eight-hour tent-to-tent time. Climbing a mountain is an amazing feeling, but the comfort and relief of being out of danger and warming up a cup of hierbabuena tea (rooibos is a rare commodity in Mexico) is equally satisfying. Before long we were in the back of a Ford4x4 heading back into town, knowing that the hard part of our journey was behind us. What beckoned was travelling, bolted climbing routes, and enough tacos to make one sick (to make Chris sick, to be precise).</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/dec28---08-back-onto-the-glacier.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/IMG_1169.JPG" class="kg-image"></figure><p>The Supertramp story doesn’t end there: there were epic multi-pitch climbing routes in El Potrero Chico, some of Mexico’s finest tequila, many more buses, more pyramids, and amazing times shared between three good friends. But we had done what we came to do. Eventually the trio disbanded and continued in different directions. Super Rick went first, and after a three-hour detention on the Mexico-Texas border (no wall yet, he reports) he made it to California’s Lake Tahoe, where he spent six glorious weeks skiing up and down the West Coast’s finest powder. Super Chris left shortly thereafter, and after two days in Mexico City sorting out his passport and visa woes, he flew to Washington DC, where he is braving the winter months in a new job. And Super Mike... some say he is still to be found in a small pueblo in Mexico, climbing harder and harder routes, living off beans and the occasional tortilla, and slowly forgetting how to speak English.</p><p>We’d like to say a very sincere thank you to The Mountain Club of South Africa and the anonymous donor, for honouring us with the Supertramp Award of 2016, that made this amazing trip possible. Also to our family and friends for putting up with our nonsense and supporting our adventure.</p><p><em>All photos by Michael Kloos</em></p><p>Also published here: <a href="https://pangaeaproject.org/primero-somos-tontos-firstly-were-fools/">https://pangaeaproject.org/primero-somos-tontos-firstly-were-fools/</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Summer in Europe]]></title><description><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k1.jpg" class="kg-image"></figure><p>This year I was lucky enough to join two UIAA youth meets. Youth rock climbing in Catalonia, organised by the FEEC, and the Kazbek mountaineering expedition, organised by the Mountaineering &amp; Climbing Association of Georgia. They were both incredible experiences, with all the fun and excitement of long multi-pitch trad</p>]]></description><link>//rdrn.me/summer-in-europe/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5bbc64bb7cc70a140e7fd114</guid><category><![CDATA[Outside]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mountains]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Arderne]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 08:20:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/DSCN6546.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k1.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/DSCN6546.JPG" alt="Summer in Europe"><p>This year I was lucky enough to join two UIAA youth meets. Youth rock climbing in Catalonia, organised by the FEEC, and the Kazbek mountaineering expedition, organised by the Mountaineering &amp; Climbing Association of Georgia. They were both incredible experiences, with all the fun and excitement of long multi-pitch trad climbing, and then the fantastic highs and lows and dreary boredom one expects from a seven-day mountaineering expedition.</p><h2 id="catalunya">Catalunya</h2><p>I was already headed to Spain this June to do some hiking in the Pyrenees with a good Spanish friend. As soon as I heard about the UIAA Global Youth Summit trip to Catalunya to do rock climbing on Montserrat and Pedraforca, it was clear my stars had aligned. I do a lot of rock climbing, but hadn’t yet had the gear or connections to do any multi-pitch trad climbing. The steep conglomerate of Montserrat and the cracked limestone of Pedraforca promised a great trip.</p><p>The tour was organised by the Federació d’Entitats Excursionistes de Catalunya (FEEC)and the group consisted of two great Catalunyan guides, five young guys from the Montserrat area, a Serbian climber, and me. We stayed in beautiful refugios at both climbing spots, and were treated to massive dinners of simple but delicious Spanish food.</p><p>We started in Montserrat, where the maze of needles and spires makes finding one’s way extremely difficult. We spent a day doing shorter slabby sport routes to get an idea of everyone’s abilities, and re-convened back at the refugio to pore over the guidebook and make plans for the next day. I joined for the more difficult route, six classic pitches up CADE (200m, 6a/Ae), a perfect crack between two spires. I seconded the whole way, and got to enjoy the fun route without much stress, especially enjoying the more difficult overhanging section near the top. Climbing with 150 metres of fresh air underneath my bum was a new experience for me.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/c_1.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>After another day of climbing, we tumbled back into the kombi and drove to Pedraforca, now in the Pyrenean foothills. It’s a stunning mountain, which gets its name from its resemblance to a giant fork. We would be climbing only the north face, to keep out of the harsh Spanish summer sun. A group of us decided to climb the massive Gran Diedre route. Unfortunately, we were limited with time and people, so I had to climb second the whole way again. Nonetheless it was an incredible climb, rising for about ten pitches above the surrounding landscape. Most of the route follows a huge dihedral, and the climbing was easy and fun, up to grade V for a few pitches.</p><p>It was a great experience and I can’t wait to get my hands on some more long trad routes. Unfortunately, I didn’t get to lead any of the long routes, so I still feel some big gaps in my experience. I was also hoping for a more varied and international group of climbers - I’m lucky enough to speak Spanish, but still would have enjoyed the chance to meet more like-minded climbers from further afield. Well done to FEEC, our awesome guides Pau and Faust, and the UIAA Youth Commission for making the trip happen.</p><h2 id="kazbek">Kazbek</h2><p>Rock climbing aside, Europe for the summer meant one thing was uppermost in my thoughts: alpinism. The UIAA had a number of youth expeditions planned, and I looked into all of them. Matterhorn - too daunting. Damavand - a bit pedestrian. Kazbek? Just right. I spoke to some more experienced friends and fellow MCSA members, and Kazbek seemed like just the place to have my next alpine experience. Steep and high and icy enough to be a challenge and a serious mountain, but straight-forward and well-trodden enough to offer some comfort to a relatively new mountaineer. My only experience before this was a guided ascent of the 6 088 metre Huayna Potosí in Bolivia, which had sealed my devotion to mountaineering.</p><p>I flew to Georgia's capital and, after some much-needed sleep under a staircase, met up with the team outside a shopping centre. Most were like me - keen to climb a mountain, but either lacking experience or willing partners. Then seven Koreans in matching shirts and hats came out of the supermarket with bundles of food and confused smiles. The trip organiser, Zura Kutchava, bundled us all into a rented minibus and soon we were pitching our tents near a beautiful old monastery, with the majestic Kazbek dominating the skyline.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k2.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>The haphazard start - the Koreans had way too much gear, and didn't seem in a rush to make a plan - foreshadowed the dominant theme for the rest of the trip. We trickled out of camp as and when we were ready, and made our way to the camp at 3 000 metres, just across a torrential river of glacial meltwater. After this, things sped up a bit, but we still spent a few hours every day waiting for everyone to be ready. I never figured out what the delays were. This was my first climb that could be described as an expedition, with horses carrying a load to the first camp, and we later descended from 3 800 metres to pick up more supplies from that camp. It was interesting (and exhausting) to see how this was done. We camped at 2 000, 3 000, 3 800 (twice) and then at 4 200 metres before the summit push to 5 047 metres. This was a lot more than most groups on the mountain, but we wanted to maximise the chances for everyone to have a successful summit. It also meant spending two nights on the frigid glacier at 4 200 metres, where I was unable to sleep in my otherwise trusty K-Way summer bag, and not helped by the fact that my tent-mates were snoring happily in their puffy expedition bags.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k3.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>This unsympathetic pair were Javier and Izidor, from Spain and Slovenia. They were both a lot more experienced than me, with experience above 7 000 metres, and summits on many of the major ranges around the world. My tent-mates were extremely helpful and I learnt so much from spending time with them (hours and hours in the tent, avoiding the sun and then the cold) and being roped in with them while crossing the frightening glacier, and for the summit. Eager and excited, but with a well-honed respect for safety, they were good teachers and I hope to do more mountaineering trips with them soon. The Koreans spoke limited English so our interactions with them didn’t get far. The group of Georgians of various experience levels provided great company every day and night, confirming time and again the Georgian reputation for kindness and hospitality.</p><p>The trip was physically demanding, with heavy packs and many metres to climb, but we had an easy pace and it wasn't a struggle. After crossing the low glacier (simple enough that there were horses crossing it) and checking in with border control at the 'meteo station', one can camp on the rugged moraine covering the glacier. From there it was a treacherous hike across the moraine, with crumbling rocks and deep crevasses, and one eye on the rock fall to the right, as helmet-sized boulders came speeding down and stopped just short of an unwelcome surprise. Then came the glacier proper – Gergeti, with cavernous crevasses and treacherous snow bridges.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/IMG_7381B.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>After that the snow covering got thicker where we made our high camp. We planned to leave at six the next morning, but six o’clock came and went, and most in the group were still inside their tents. This frustrated my one tent-mate past his breaking point, and after walking around agitating everyone to get going, he eventually gave up and set off by himself. This catalysed a bit of group movement and we set off not too far behind him. It was a sad moment, and reflected a brewing problem in the group dynamic. It's a straightforward hike to the summit, with a relatively steep section at the end. We had a stunning view of the Caucasus from the shoulder, with Elbrus visible in the distance, but unfortunately the clouds came in as we did the last hundred metres, and we had a very white scene at the top. Still an awesome feeling to stand atop a mountain as imposing as Kazbek.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k5.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>We hiked in teams of five and, apart from some tired-out Koreans stumbling on the descent, everything went smoothly. For me, the most tiring part of the entire trip was probably digging in and building walls for our tents on the glacier. My tent-mates decided they'd had enough and left the beginner to do the job. Luckily I was having fun and continued working on our fortification, because about an hour later a huge Georgian search-and-rescue helicopter landed a stone's throw away and tried its best to send our camp tumbling along the glacier.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k4.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p>This helicopter revealed a very sad and real side to mountaineering. Two girls we'd befriended a few nights before at the lower camp, and who we'd seen coming down from the summit, had tried to descend the glacier without a rope. Although they were following the footsteps of a big roped team, a day of beating sun had made conditions precarious. One of the two made an unlucky step, and fell into a crevasse. She died quite soon after. This tragic event served as a sober reminder of the very real dangers in mountaineering. Their risky behaviour and the preventable nature of the accident only reinforced this lesson for me.</p><p>It was an amazing trip, and I learnt so much as a mountaineer and individual. My thanks go to Zura, the capable, lively and infinitely patient team leader, and the Mountaineering &amp; Climbing Association of Georgia. Also to the UIAA for making the event possible, and the MCSA for making my participation possible.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//rdrn.me/content/images/2018/10/k6.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Summer in Europe"></figure><p><em>All Kazbek photos by FJ Pascual.</em></p><p>Partially posted here: <a href="https://lossupertramps.wordpress.com/2016/07/05/kazbek-with-the-uiaa/">https://lossupertramps.wordpress.com/2016/07/05/kazbek-with-the-uiaa/</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>